<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Quantum memristors for neuromorphic quantum machine learning</title>
				<funder ref="#_A9CKwCY #_3CgpHpU #_KbcCDg8">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_JW4kJyn">
					<orgName type="full">Ministry for Digital Transformation and of Civil Service of the Spanish Government</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_DymPuZ4">
					<orgName type="full">European Union</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Lucas</forename><surname>Lamata</surname></persName>
							<email>llamata@us.es</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departamento de Física Atómica</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Molecular, y Nuclear</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Facultad de Física</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Sevilla</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Apartado 1065</postBox>
									<postCode>E-41080</postCode>
									<settlement>Sevilla</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Quantum memristors for neuromorphic quantum machine learning</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3C5D127F8D91DA62FEBE240D0050AB5F</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-25T17:07+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Quantum machine learning may permit to realize more efficient machine learning calculations with near-term quantum devices. Among the diverse quantum machine learning paradigms which are currently being considered, quantum memristors are promising as a way of combining, in the same quantum hardware, a unitary evolution with the nonlinearity provided by the measurement and feedforward. Thus, an efficient way of deploying neuromorphic quantum computing for quantum machine learning may be enabled.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Quantum machine learning is an emerging field inside quantum technologies, which may enable to carry out more efficient machine learning calculations with near-term quantum devices <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. It is apparent that a purely quantum unitary evolution is not enough for an efficient learning process, which implies irreversibility to some extent <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>. Therefore, most quantum learning algorithms imply some variant of the so-called quantum-classical protocols, such as variational quantum eigensolvers <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, quantum Boltzmann machines <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, quantum approximate optimization algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, and quantum reinforcement learning protocols <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Besides the basic digital quantum circuit model, all these algorithms include quantum measurements and feedforward in some part of the execution, with subsequent further unitary evolution, further classical part, and so on. Usually, one considers a universal quantum computer based on the digital paradigm for carrying out all these quantum algorithms. However, it may be sensible to employ specialized quantum hardware, which incorporates ab initio both the unitary evolution and the quantum measurement part in the same building block. This is what a quantum memristor <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> may enable.</p><p>A quantum memristor <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> is a quantum device that is composed of a twodimensional quantum system, in the most basic instances, together with a weak measurement and feedforward, in the same basic unit. Its properties are that it can sustain a unitary evolution, and in the classical limit it behaves with a hysteresis dynamics, such as a classical memristor <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. Several of these units may be coupled together to form a network of quantum memristors <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23]</ref>, which may be regarded as a neuromorphic quantum architecture. Even though it is not obvious at first sight that this quantum paradigm may carry out more efficient quantum computing protocols than other architectures, it has the basic ingredients of unitary evolution, nonlinearity provided by the measurement, and a scalable architecture. Therefore, quantum memristors could be useful bricks for quantum machine learning devices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Quantum memristors for neuromorphic quantum machine learning</head><p>Machine learning aims at having a computing device that can acquire information from the outer world, so called environment, and use that information to improve its performance for some task, in each iteration <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. This is referred to as learning from the environment. The idea is that interacting with the external world in successive steps, may enable the machine to improve its behaviour for the desired task, sometimes even at superhuman level <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. Even though classical machine learning already works extremely well, which is evidenced in the multiple daily life applications we enjoy, it is true that processing an increasing amount of data with algorithms that do not scale optimally for this information size is posing a difficulty both in terms of resources and energy consumption. Quantum computers may be a way forward to scale up machine learning computations due to the quantum parallelism, quantum speedup at least for certain kinds of problems, and more efficient energy use in the computing process. However, it is not obvious at first sight which, if any, of the multiple proposed quantum machine learning algorithms may be useful in the short or mid-term for carrying out tasks in better or at least complementary ways to existing classical machine learning protocols. Some of the quantum machine learning protocols rely on the good connection of quantum systems to linear algebra, via, e.g., the quantum phase estimation algorithm, efficient distance computations, etc <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. This kind of algorithms normally rely on a single quantum evolution followed by a final measurement. However, they often require a very large number of qubits which is not accesible today or in the near future. Other kinds of quantum machine learning protocols, which have less rigorous evidence of speedup, but nevertheless may be carried out with noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers, are included in the paradigm of classical-quantum protocols. This consists of an iteration of several instances of quantum evolution followed by a measurement, where the subsequent quantum evolution depends on the outcome of the previous measurement, via feedforward. This includes variational quantum eigensolvers, quantum Boltzmann machines, quantum approximate optimization algorithms, quantum reinforcement learning, and quantum memristors.</p><p>Of all the existing quantum paradigms for classical-quantum protocols, an appealing of quantum memristors is its in-built modular structure combining in the same unit the quantum coherence via the two-level quantum system and the measurement part, necessary for the nonlinear evolution and the learning process. This seems convenient for scaling up these kinds of protocols involving several iterations of quantum and classical dynamics with intermediate measurements. This is at variance, for example, with the field of quantum simulations, where normally one carries out a single quantum dynamics followed by a final measurement, and more standard quantum architectures already perform very efficiently <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>.</p><p>It is hard to really predict whether this quantum paradigm of a network of quantum memristors for neuromorphic quantum machine learning will perform better than classical machine learning protocols such as standard neural networks, but this is also a usual problem when comparing a neural network with another one in the classical realm. We, as humans evolved from animals, deal with a very reduced amount of degrees of freedom in our conscious thoughts, as compared with the amount of neurons we have in our brains. Nevertheless, we are perfectly aware of the capabilities of our brains to carry out conscious and useful thinking and knowledge acquisition, which enables us to live in the technological world we have collectively created. I cannot really predict if we will ever be able to understand the inner workings of our brains [27] or of an increasingly complex neural network technology, either classical or quantum. Perhaps it may not even be possible physically or from a computability point of view, but it may not even matter. From a purely pragmatic point of view, if we can use increasingly complex neural networks for an increasingly more advanced set of uses, we may enjoy of unprecedented capabilities for enhancing both our species and the other living species well-being.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Possible implementations with current quantum devices</head><p>Implementations of quantum memristors with current quantum platforms have been proposed in quantum photonics, superconducting circuits, trapped ions, and polaritons <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. An experimental implementation in a quantum photonics chip has evidenced that the concept of quantum memristor can be realized in real quantum systems, behaving as expected <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. Other platforms such as superconducting circuits and trapped ions are also promising for this purpose, and the emergence, in the past few years, of Rydberg atoms as a scalable and controllable quantum platform may also suggest that this concrete platform could be successfully employed for this purpose <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[28]</ref>. The same protocols employed in the fast-developing realm of scalable quantum error correction, for error detection and correction via measurement and feedforward <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[29]</ref>, may be directly employed for deploying a scalable network of quantum memristors. Thus, the paradigm of scalable neuromorphic quantum machine learning seems plausible to realize in the mid-term with foreseeable technology <ref type="bibr">[30]</ref>. This could also be combined with the tools of digital-analog quantum simulations, computing, and machine learning, which may enable faster scalability and quantum control combined <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">32]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>Quantum machine learning may enable quantum devices to carry out more efficient machine learning tasks in the near term. To this aim, the combination of unitary evolution with classical optimization, in sequential iterative steps, named quantum-classical protocols, seems a promising path for noisy-intermediate scale quantum computers. In this way, the nonlinear character of the quantum measurement process provides a crucial ingredient for a quantum learning beyond what purely reversible unitary evolution could provide. Among the diverse quantum-classical paradigms appearing for quantum machine learning, quantum memristors seem promising because of their modular structure that combines in the same hardware unit, the quantum memristor, both the unitary and measurement parts, as well as the feedforward. In this way, and similarly to specialized classical neuromorphic hardware, which is expected to implement neural networks in a more efficient way, quantum memristors may enable one to scale up quantum neural networks and quantum neuromorphic computing more successfully and enable neuromorphic quantum machine learning with near term devices. This may permit to scale up machine learning calculations for those tasks which could be properly mapped to this emerging quantum paradigm. Finally, the concept of a quantum memristor network may be also related to the emerging paradigm of digital-analog quantum computation and simulation, and its connection to machine learning, namely, digital-analog quantum machine learning. This is apparent, as quantum memristors are discrete units, with digital character, and at the same time they have analog ingredients in their execution, such as the weak measurement or continuous time unitary dynamics in each unit. This could allow one for both faster scalability and versatility of the device.</p></div>		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>I acknowledge the support from grants <rs type="grantNumber">PID2022-136228NB-C21</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">PID2022-136228NB-C22</rs> funded by <rs type="grantNumber">MCIN/AEI/10.13039/50110001103</rs> and "<rs type="projectName">ERDF A way of making Europe</rs>". This work has also been financially supported by the <rs type="funder">Ministry for Digital Transformation and of Civil Service of the Spanish Government</rs> through the <rs type="projectName">QUANTUM ENIA</rs> project <rs type="projectName">call -Quantum Spain</rs> project, and by the <rs type="funder">European Union</rs> through the <rs type="programName">Recovery, Transformation and Resilience Plan -NextGenerationEU within the framework of the "Digital Spain 2026 Agenda</rs>".</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_A9CKwCY">
					<idno type="grant-number">PID2022-136228NB-C21</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_3CgpHpU">
					<idno type="grant-number">PID2022-136228NB-C22</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_JW4kJyn">
					<idno type="grant-number">MCIN/AEI/10.13039/50110001103</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">ERDF A way of making Europe</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_KbcCDg8">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">QUANTUM ENIA</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_DymPuZ4">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">call -Quantum Spain</orgName>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">Recovery, Transformation and Resilience Plan -NextGenerationEU within the framework of the &quot;Digital Spain 2026 Agenda</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comprehensive review of quantum machine learning: from NISQ to fault tolerance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yunfei</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Junyu</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rep. Prog. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">116402</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum machine learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Biamonte</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">549</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">74001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum machine learning and quantum biomimetics: A perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lamata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mach. Learn.: Sci. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">33002</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lamata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Quantum Machine Learning Implementations: Proposals and Experiments</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2300059</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A variational eigenvalue solver on a photonic quantum processor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Peruzzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Comm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4213</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From transistor to trapped-ion computers for quantum chemistry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Casanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3589</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Variational Quantum Eigensolver: A review of methods and best practices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tilly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">986</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum Boltzmann machine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Amin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Andriyash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rolfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kulchytskyy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Melko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review X</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21050</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Farhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Goldstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gutmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1411.4028</idno>
		<title level="m">A quantum approximate optimization algorithm</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basic protocols in quantum reinforcement learning with superconducting circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lamata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1609</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measurement-based adaptation protocol with quantum reinforcement learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Albarrán-Arriagada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Retamal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Solano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lamata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42315</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reconstruction of a photonic qubit state with reinforcement learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Quantum Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1800074</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum reinforcement learning in the presence of thermal dissipation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Olivera-Atencio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lamata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Morillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Casado-Pascual</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14128</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Machine learning &amp; artificial intelligence in the quantum domain: a review of recent progress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Dunjko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Briegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rep. Prog. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">74001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Memristors go quantum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lamata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Phot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">265</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pfeiffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Egusquiza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Di</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ventra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sanz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Solano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quantum Memristors, Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">29507</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Salmilehto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Deppe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Di</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ventra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sanz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Solano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quantum Memristors with Superconducting Circuits, Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42044</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sanz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lamata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Solano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Quantum Memristors in Quantum Photonics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">80801</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental photonic quantum memristor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Spagnolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Phot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">318</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum memristors: a new approach to neuromorphic computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Forsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Stremoukhov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Frolova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Khabarova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kolachevsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics-Uspekhi</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">855</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Ventra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Pershin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Memristors and Memelements</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entangled quantum memristors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">62605</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tripartite Entanglement in Quantum Memristors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Applied</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">34004</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Norvig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Artificial Intelligence: A Modern Approach</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pearson</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hassabis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nobel</forename><surname>Lecture</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2024/12/hassabis-lecture.pdf" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Georgescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ashhab</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Nori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Mod. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">153</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Many-body physics with individually controlled Rydberg atoms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Browaeys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Thierry</forename><surname>Lahaye</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">132</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Logical quantum processor based on reconfigurable atom arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bluvstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">626</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">58</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital-Analog Quantum Simulations with Superconducting Circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lamata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Parra-Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sanz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Solano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Phys.: X</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1457981</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lamata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:2411.10744</idno>
		<title level="m">Digital-Analog Quantum Machine Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
